Guide to the A. J. Macdonald Writings on American Utopian Communities
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Integral Phalanx (Sangamon County, Illinois), 1845–1847, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Leaves 250–252
  See also verso of leaf 625 in "Sketch of the Life of Frances Wright."
- Integral Phalanx (Sangamon County, Illinois), 1845–1847 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  Leaves 253–254
  Printed report by the association secretary clipped from the New York Herald Tribune (1845).
- Leraysville Phalanx (Bradford County, Pennsylvania), 1844, 1844–1852 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Leaves 255–259
  Includes printed stock certificate for one share in the Phalanx sold to John Joseph Lang, May 1844.
- Clarkson Industrial Association (Monroe County, New York), 1844, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Leaves 260–270
  History of the association provided by John Greig of Rochester, New York.
- Prairie Home Community (West Liberty, Ohio), 1844 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Leaves 271–292
  Extracted from "Travels in search of employment." Notes from Macdonald's visits to "Prarie Home" from August to October 1844.
- Grand Prairie Harmonial Institute (Tippecanoe County, Indiana), 1853 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Leaves 293–300
  Includes notes from Cincinnati printer Mr. William McDiarmid, printed Constitution of the Grand Prairie Harmonial Institute (1853), and a newspaper clipping.
- Grand Prairie Home Community (Indiana), undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Leaves 301–302
  Newspaper clipping affixed to a postal wrapper addressed to Edward Walker & Sons, New York.
- Yellow Springs Community (Greene County, Ohio), 1825, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Leaves 303–305
  Notes and newspaper clipping with unsigned "Reminisences of the Community at Yellow Springs, Ohio."
- Guatemala Experiment (Fourier), 1843, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Leaf 306
  Newspaper clipping from Owen's New Moral World (1845).
- Marlborough Association (Clinton County, Ohio), 1841, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  Leaves 307–315
  Transcriptions of a history by Esther Ann Lukens of New Garden, Ohio, and "Causes of Failure" by Thomas Moore.
- Colony of Bethel (Shelby County, Missouri), 1852 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  Leaves 316–325
  Transcription of a narrative by "my friend Wilhelm Weitling, editor of the Republik Arbeiter who visited the place in 1852."
- Raritan Bay Union (Perth Amboy, New Jersey), 1853 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  Leaves 326–331
  Report of Macdonald's September 1853 visit, unsigned newspaper clipping from the New York Herald (1853); printed preamble and by-laws for the community (1853).
- One-Mentian Community (Monroe County, Pennsylvania), 1844, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Leaves 332–337
  A history "compiled from various sources" with John Hooper's letter to the editor of the Regenerator clipped from an unidentified newspaper.
- Moorhouse Union (Hamilton County, New York), 1843–1844, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  Leaves 338–343
- Alphadelphia Phalanx (Kalamazoo County, Michigan), 1846–1847, 1852 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Leaves 344–350
  Information obtained from Dr. H. R. Schetterly of Ann Arbor; noted at end: "written Aug 30th 1852."
- Hunt's Experiment of Equality (Mukwonago Township, Waukesha County, Wisconsin), 1843–1845, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  Leaves 351–362
  On verso of leaf 362: "This is complete save I have written again to Hunt about the property Sept 12 1852."
- Sylvania Association (Pike County, Pennsylvania),1843–1845, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Leaves 363–381
  Contains notes, printed items including a prospectus, constitution, by-laws, and stock certificate (1843), and second manuscript titled "A Dialogue concerning the Sylvania Association" including "Sylvanians' Prayer" attributed to J. D. Pierson. Noted on verso of leaf 381: "Read by Mr. Kellogg / wants reading once / more."
- Spring Farm Association (Sheboygan County, Wisconsin), 1846–1848, 1852 May 6 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Leaves 382–384
  Noted on verso of leaf 384: "written May 6, 1852."
- Second Section of the Social Reformers Co-operative Emigration Society (Mukwonago, Wisconsin), 1843–1852, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  Leaves 385–387
  Includes printed broadside Prospectus and Plan of Operations of the Second Section of The Social Reformers Co-operative Emigration Society (1843).
- Jefferson County Industrial Association (Jefferson County, New York), 1843, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  Leaves 388–390
- Haverstraw Community (Haverstraw, New York), 1826, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Leaves 391–392
  Same organization as the Franklin Community (leaf 417).
- Brotherhood of the Union (Ohio), 1850–1851, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Leaf 393
- Blue Spring Community (Bloomington, Indiana), 1826–1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  Leaf 394
- D. A. Brooke's Experiment (Warren County, Ohio), 1844, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  Leaves 395–399
  Account extracted from "Travels in search of employment." Visited in October 1844 after leaving the Prairie Home Community.
- Forestville Community (Greene County, New York), 1825, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  Leaf 400
  Same organization as Coxsackie Community (leaves 418–419).
- LaGrange Phalanx (LaGrange County, Indiana), undated, 1852 August 31 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  Leaves 401–401a
  Noted as "Mostly from Schettling / done / Aug 31 1852."
- Kendal Community (Stark County, Ohio), 1826–1828, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  Leaves 402–405
- Auxiliary Branch of the Association of all Classes of all Nations, 1836, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  Leaves 406–408
- Social Reform Unity (Pike County, Pennsylvania), 1842, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  Leaves 409–415
  Includes information on Goose Pond Community (Pike County, Pennsylvania), 1843, and printed Constitution and Laws of the Social Reform Unity (1842).
- Garden Grove (Iowa), 1848, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  Leaf 416
- Franklin Community (New York), 1826, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  Leaf 417
  Same as Haverstraw Community (leaves 391–392).
- Coxsackie Community (Greene County, New York), 1826, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  Leaves 418–419
  Same as Forestville Community (leaf 400).
- St. Louis Reform Association (St. Louis, Missouri), 1851, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  Leaf 420
  Includes information on Co-operating Society of Alleghany County (Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania), 1825.
- Communia Working Men's League (Clayton County, Iowa), 1850 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  Leaf 421
  Holds printed constitution clipped from unidentified newspaper.
- Convention at Boston of the Friends of Association, 1843, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  Leaves 422–423
- National Reform Association, 1845, and Commonwealth Society (New York City), 1819, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  Leaf 424
- Orson S. Murray, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  Leaves 425–427
  Leaf 428 appears in Robert Owen's folder (leaves 501–523).
- A Brief Sketch of the Life and Writings of Charles Fourier, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Leaves 429–431
  Clipping from two undated issues of The Morning Star, and People's Economist: Advocate of the Tropical Emigration Society.
- Ebenezer Community (Erie County, New York), 1853, 1853 September (Box 2, Folder 58)
  Leaves 432–436
  Contains notes from his visit on September 6, 1853.
- United Brethren or Moravians, 1745, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
  Leaves 437–445
  Historical essay using material copied from various sources.
- Jemima Wilkinson, 1780, 1853 May (Box 2, Folder 60)
  Leaves 446–451
  Compiled from John Warner Barber's Historical Collections of New York (1851).
- Cincinnati Brotherhood (Cincinnati, Ohio), 1845–1848, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  Leaves 452–455
  Includes an undated clipping from The Univercoelum and Spiritual Philosopher.
- Spiritual Community (Mountain Cove, Virginia), 1853, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  Leaves 456–458
- Principles of Divine Revelations and Voice of Mankind by and through A. J. Davis, 1853 March (Box 2, Folder 63)
  Leaf 459
- Harmonial Brotherhood (Hartford, Connecticut), 1851, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  Leaf 459a
  Material quoted from Andrew Jackson Davis's The Great Harmonia.
- Venezuelan Experiment of the Tropical Emigration Society, 1844–1846, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
  Leaves 460–484
  Essay on John Adolphus Etzler and his followers. Noted on verso of leaf 483: "Read by John Maine / (formerly a member of / the association) / Feb 1853 / and pronounced by him a / very impartial, and so far as / he knows, correct account of / the affair. / AJM"
- Zoar German Community (Tuscarawas County, Ohio), 1819, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  Leaves 485–492
  Notes from "Travels in search of employment" describing his visit in October 1844, an undated graphite drawing of the community, and clipping from an unidentified newspaper (1853).
- The Dunkers (German Baptists, Euphrates, Pennsylvania), 1725, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  Leaves 493–496
- McKean County German Association (Pennsylvania) and The Social Unity (Pike County, Pennsylvania), 1843, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
  Leaf 497
  Both short entries copied from The Phalanx (1843); verso of leaf has the start of a letter to "J. A. Paine."
- Brazilian Experiment, 1841, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  Leaf 498
- Society of the United Germans (Teutonia, Ohio), 1827, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  Leaf 499
- German Catholic Community (near Milwaukee, Wisconsin), 1853 June 18 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  Leaf 500
  Holds a newspaper clipping from the New York Tribune.
- Robert Owen
  - Sketch of work and principles, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
    Leaves 428, 501–522
    Memoir covering Owen's visits to New York and Albany and his interactions with Owen and Julius R. Ames. Also present is an outline of Owen's social principles, and an undated wood engraving of "Owen's model Phalanx" clipped from an unidentifed publication.
  - Biography clipped from The New Moral World (1840) (Box 4, Folder 93)
    Leaf 523
  - New Lanark, Scotland, Robert Owen's experiment, 1799–1829, 1852 March 7 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    Leaves 524–534
    Signed and dated: "A.J.M March 7th 1852 / 75 Nassau St. rear / Room 28."
  - History of the Community Experiments at New Harmony (Posey County, Indiana), 1825–1827, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
    Leaves 535–577
  - New Harmony in 1842, 1853 December 18 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    Leaves 578–616
    "Compiled from 'Travels in Search of Employment'"; signed and dated on the verso of leaf 614: "Harmony Complete / 82 leaves here / without printed extracts / Dec 18th 1853 / AJMc." Annotated below that: "leaves 615 & 616 wanting / Jan. 6 1870 / A.V.N." A section on Macluria begins on leaf 594.
- Frances Wright
  - Sketch of the Life of Frances Wright, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    Leaves 617–625
    Verso of leaf 625 carries information on Integral Phalanx (Sangamon County, Illinois).
  - Nashoba (Shelby County, Tennessese), 1825–1828, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
    Leaves 626–638a
- The Shakers
  The most extensive section of Macdonald's papers is devoted to the Shakers and covers all aspects of their life, community, and beliefs. Much of the material in this section is written in a script that is smaller and neat, suggesting that Macdonald may have had someone transcribing for him.
  - "Millenial Church" or "United Society of Believers" / Outline of their History, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
    Leaves 639–663
    Includes sections on History (from leaf 639), Statistics (643), List of Communities (644), Beliefs (646), Worship (647), Government (649), Laws (652), Bibliography (654), Belief in Spirits (655), Sexual Intercourse (657), Morals (658), Economics (660), Buildings (662), and Benevolence (663). Macdonald attached a small paper to the first leaf with the note: "Complete except / page 6 / 19 / 23 / the Government must / be revised."
  - Extract from Lamson's description of the Shaker community at Hancock, Berkshire Co., Mass., undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
    Leaves 664–667
  - Extract from Colonel Maxwell's description of the Shaker Community at Enfield, Hartford Co., Conn., undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    Leaves 668–669
  - Extract from Stewart's description of the Shaker community at New Lebanon, Columbia Co., N.Y., undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
    Leaf 670
  - Visit to Watervliet, 1847, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
    Leaves 671–676
    Narrative of Macdonald's visit on September 1, 1847, with his friend "S," possibly Smith the author of "Narrative of Four Months residence among the Shakers at Watervliet" (leaves 685–724).
  - Visit to "Union Village" near Lebanon, Ohio, 1844, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
    Leaves 677–681, with one unnumbered leaf
    Narrative of Macdonald's visit on September 6, 1844. The unnumbered leaf contains a quotation in an unidentified hand from Travels in America, Performed in 1806 by Thomas Ashe (London; Newburyport: reprinted for William Sawyer & Co., 1808), with an autograph note by Macdonald: "you must still see if the above really means 'Union Home' June 7th 1853."
  - Shakers Settlement in Kentucky, 1852 November 6 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    Leaves 682–684
    Copied from various sources.
  - Narrative of Four Months residence among the Shakers at Watervliet, 1842, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    Leaves 685–724
    Twenty-one numbered essays by "an intimate and esteemed Friend" of Macdonald who arrived in New York in August 1842 and, unable to find employment in that city or in Albany, took up residence with the Shakers. The author is partially identified by Macdonald's inscription on verso of leaf 724: "Smith's narrative / read to Smith Nov. 9 / 1851 at Troy." The narrative's opening line "My Friend, The following Account of my brief experience among the Shakers..." was annotated, likely by Smith, "To A. J. Macdonald."
  - Extract from "The Great Harmonia" by A. J. Davis, 1852, undated (Box 3, Folder 86)
    Leaf 725
    On the verso in Macdonald's hand: "Ann Lee / A. J. Davis / to go with / Shaker article"; and "Leaves 726–9 / wanting Jan. 6. 1870 / A.V.N."
  - Watervliet, undated (Box 3, Folder 87)
    Leaf 730
    Graphite drawing of a dwelling house, not signed or dated but presumably made during his visit in 1847 (see leaves 671–676); inscribed along left edge: "Mrs W. Kellog - [Gray?]"
- Constitution of the Progressive Fraternity, Harmonia, Cherokee County, Kansas, 1865, undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
  Leaf 731
  Transcription of a constitution signed by F. T. Thomas, secretary, and W. Nicely, president. The community was located on the Spring River.
- Alphabetical index of communities, with leaf numbers, circa 1865 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  Prepared by George Washington Noyes (1823–1870), brother of John Humphrey Noyes; see letter in Box 3, folder 91; accompanied by a twewntieth-century typed transcript.
  The index was published in The Circular, vol. 5, no. 31, October 19, 1868, page 244.
- Front cover of album formerly holding Macdonald manuscripts, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 90)
- Back cover of album formerly holding Macdonald manuscripts, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  The inside of this cover holds a letter from Victor Cragin Noyes (1847–1905) to his father John Humphrey Noyes, dated October 10, 1865, in which he describes his work on indexing the manuscripts. Victor Noyes describes some of the drawings he isolated from the manuscripts; the line is followed by a note: "These pictures are retained at O.C. [Oneida Community] J.H.N."